This is דף כ"ז Daf Chaf-Zayin but we start a little bit
on the bottom of כ"ו עמוד ב' Chaf-Vav amud Beis
and we start with
where the גמרא Gemara says the following.
Hold on.
כאן לאוקשו כאן להתיר. kan l'oksho kan l'hatiro. So the question was
if you need in order for the מנחה Mincha to be valid,
we start on the first wide line of כ"ו עמוד ב'. Chaf-Vav
amud Beis. If you need in order for the מנחה Mincha to
be valid for the קומץ Kometz to be mostly burning by fire,
you know, if the fire seized most of it, is on most
of it, how can you put it up right before sunset which
we sort of inferred from the previous ברייתא Beraita and allow it
to continue burning? And the גמרא's Gemara answer interestingly is yes, that
that can work, that the מנחה Mincha does not become valid until
the fire seizes most of it, as long as you put it
on the fire when you did the act of the עבודה Avoda
was right before sunset. And once it's up there it remains up
there and then once the fire has seized most of it even
if that happens at night, that is when it becomes valid. And
we discuss that that is a phenomena that you have elsewhere where
you might consider that a process needs to finish by itself in
order to be considered done as long as the human activity is
done in the proper time, like putting something on a fire right
before שבת Shabbos is over and it burns on and it cooks
over שבת. Shabbat. I made that some joke, I think that's just
about right. Okay. And cooks on over שבת Shabbat because and that
would be considered an act of cooking because it was done on,
it was placed
on the fire on שבת. Shabbat.
So that seems to be how the גמרא Gemara is understanding this.
So now we continue. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar מתני לה matni lah
מבוא השמש mevo hashemesh ומוקינה בפקועין. umukinah bepikuin.
Can I ask a question?
No, let's first get to the משנה, Mishna, then you can ask
your questions. Let's catch up. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar מתני לה matni
lah מבוא השמש mevo hashemesh ומוקינה בפקועין. umukinah bepikuin. Now רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar says that we are not talking
about putting up the מנחה Mincha right before sunset, we're talking about
putting it up even after sunset. Now the קומץ. Kometz. Now how
can you do that? The קומץ Kometz has to be offered during
the day. So he says the ברייתא Beraita is talking about things
that popped off of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. And if they popped off
of the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, then as long as it was put then
you can restore it even after nightfall. So according to him, he
might say that everything has to be during the day
but if it pops off, if a מנחה Mincha pops off, if
the קומץ Kometz pops off, then you can restore it during nightfall.
Right. And that's like a normal principle that we have by sunset.
I've seen that happening with an עולה olah
more so than with a מנחה. mincha.
That is true, but little pieces
maybe. וכן כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי ינאי v'chen ki asa
Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yanai בפקועין, bepikuin,
that it's the פקועין, pikuin, things that pop off. All right, so
we have the problem about it's felt about burning the קומץ Kometz
after sunset and we are saying you cannot לכתחילה lechat'chila burn it
after sunset. It either means you started before sunset and it continued
or maybe you burnt everything that was requisite before sunset and then
things popped off. Okay, so now it continues. ומי אמר רבי ינאי
הכי, umi amar Rabbi Yanai hachi, does רבי ינאי Rabbi Yanai really
say that, that if it pops off you restore it after sunset?
והאמר רבי ינאי ve'amar Rabbi Yanai קטורת שפקעה מעגבי המזבח אפילו קירטין
שבה אין מחזירין אותן. ketoret shepak'ah me'agabei hamizbe'ach afilu kirtin shebah ein
machzirin otan.
That if the קטורת, Ketoret, now this is not the קומץ, Kometz,
this is the קטורת Ketoret that you burn on the מזבח הזהב,
Mizbe'ach hazahav, if it pops off of the מזבח Mizbe'ach even the
tiniest little cube or whatever, piece, you would not put it back.
You can't? You cannot. No, you cannot. Okay. Say why? Well, let's
see what the explanation is. ותני רבי חנינא בר מניומי בדברי רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב vesani Rabbi Chanina bar Minyumi bedivrei Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov as רבי
חנינא בר מניומי Rabbi Chanina bar Minyumi teaches in the words of
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, אשר תאכל האש את
העולה על המזבח, asher tochal ha'esh et ha'olah al hamizbe'ach, that it's
based on the פסוק, pasuk, how do we know you put things
back on if they fall off? Because the verse says that the
fire consumes the עולה olah on the altar. So what altar are
we referring to? We are on כ"ו עמוד ב' Chaf-Vav amud Beis
at six lines from the bottom. איכולי עולה אתה מחזיר, ichulei olah
atah machzir, you return things that were consumed like the עולה olah
you return, ואי אתה מחזיר איכולי קטורת. ve'ei attah machzir ichulei ketoret.
And not the frankincense, the incense rather. So what is his point?
His point here is the difference between the outer מזבח Mizbe'ach and
the inner מזבח. Mizbe'ach. The idea of that if something falls off
the מזבח Mizbe'ach you can put it back on, that's talking about
the outer מזבח, Mizbe'ach, we learn that from the פסוק pasuk of
את העולה על המזבח et ha'olah al hamizbe'ach that you keep the
stuff on the fire even you know all night, right, but we
never say this by the inner מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So the קטורת Ketoret
that's burnt on the golden מזבח Mizbe'ach we don't say. Now the
logic is that we're not talking about things that לכתחילה lechat'chila you
could put on the fire at night like the, although ironically that
is the פסוק pasuk by the עולה, olah, like the limbs of
the עולה olah or the fat of the עולה, olah, we're talking
about things that you really are only allowed לכתחילה, lechat'chila, meaning not
לכתחילה lechat'chila as opposed to בדיעבד, bedi'avad, that at the initial placing
must be on the. during the day. So for example, the קטורת
ketoret is burnt, the incense is burnt, but it has to be
placed on the altar during the day. The קומץ kometz and the
לבונה levonah are burnt, they have to be placed during the day.
So things that have to be placed during the day, if they
were placed during the day and then they fell off, can they
be placed back at night? So he says that's only a הלכה
halacha by the outer מזבח, mizbe'ach, not the inner. So the burning
of the incense on the golden מזבח, mizbe'ach, on the inner מזבח,
mizbe'ach, if it fell off at night cannot be restored.
If it fell off during the day, you would restore it.
Okay. Presumably, right. Presumably this is specifically an issue of night.
Although actually I must admit that I might be that might not
be true, he might be saying it in general you don't restore
anything, but logically this makes more sense to be talking about the
night problem.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says סמי מכאן קטורת. sami mikan ketoret.
So fine, according to him you would have to take out the
word קטורת, ketoret, that קטורת ketoret is not something that you would
put back at night. אמר רב אסי: Amar Rav Assi: but you
would still put the קומץ kometz and לבונה levonah because that's the
outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, כי פשט רבי
אלעזר במנחות, ki pashat Rabbi Elazar bemenachos, when Rabbi Elazar was learning
מנחות, Menachos, בעי הכי, ba'ei hachi, he asked the following question: קומץ
שסידרו. kometz shesidro.
Now we're going to talk about a totally different concern. Until now
the concern has been how much of the קומץ kometz has to
burn for it to be considered like the קרבן korban was offered
up, like the קומץ kometz was offered and the מנחה mincha is
good. Is it that the fire just begins touching it or was
directly put on the fire or does the fire have to seize
it, and that is a process that takes time? And as a
result we spoke about putting it on before sunset and it finishes
after sunset and things popping off. Now we are turning to just
some totally unrelated random little things about how you burn, I mean
they're not random, how you burn the קומץ. kometz. So let's take
a look. He asked the following question: קומץ שסידרו, kometz shesidro, you
put the קומץ, kometz, you arranged it, meaning you put it on
the wood on the altar, וסידר עליו את המערכה, vesidar alav et
hama'aracha, but then you put the fire above it, not below it.
You put it on a flat part of the מזבח mizbe'ach and
you put then the firewood and the fire above it. מהו? mahu?
What's the הלכה? halacha? Is that considered offering it up? דרך הקטרה
בכך? derech haktara bekach? Is that the way somebody offers up incense,
you know, burns incense, although it's not incense but again the verb
here is an incense verb or actually as we saw before it's
a verb about the pillar of smoke. Is that the way you
raise the smoke of something? Is that sufficiently the way? או אין
דרך הקטרה בכך? o ein derech haktara bekach? Or is it not
sufficiently the way? And the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, unanswered.
Wait, the מערכה ma'aracha always has to be there first? What? The
מערכה ma'aracha always has to be there first?
Yeah, but you put it on a space in the מזבח mizbe'ach
where there wasn't a מערכה, ma'aracha, it doesn't cover every square inch.
Now again, what I would ask is the question about how much
according to at least רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, if you remember רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishna says I don't care if
you use a vessel, you don't use a vessel, how you get
it to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, how much is there a formal act
of placing it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the קומץ, kometz, or is
it just getting it burnt? That's the issue we raised yesterday. This
question of דרך הקטרה בכך, derech haktara bekach, is this the normal
way, often is used by way of saying is this considered a
legitimate act? Is this enough classic way of doing this act that
it falls within the parameters of doing the act? Read that way
this still would be the question of that you need an act
of placing it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But I think you could
read it another way, that maybe the smoke doesn't go up as
well, you know, if things are under the fire but on top
of the firewood it's not going to rise as well. So it's
not just a question about the process, it's a question about the
result as well. So the גמרא Gemara does not have an answer.
Let's see one more related question. And this really gets us away
from the מנחה mincha question. בעי חזקיה, Ba'ei Chizkiya, חזקיה Chizkiya asked:
אברים שסידרן וסידר עליהן את המערכה. evarim shesidran vesidar aleihen et hama'aracha.
So you put the limbs of an עולה olah up on the
מזבח mizbe'ach and similarly, first you put them on the flat part
of the מזבח mizbe'ach and then you put the firewood on top.
So now we're not talking about burning the קומץ, kometz, we're talking
about burning the limbs of the עולה. olah. מהו? mahu? What's the
הלכה? halacha? Now here it's not just a question of is it
the normal way, we've got a פסוק. pasuk. What does the פסוק
pasuk say you do by an עולה? olah? על העצים, Al ha'etzim,
אמר רחמנא. amar rachmana. It says you put the limbs on the
wood. על העצים, Al ha'etzim, דווקא? davka? Does that mean specifically that
way? The limbs of the עולה olah have to be on the
firewood? דווקא על העצים, Davka al ha'etzim, is it specifically mean that?
או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say כיון דכתיב קרא אחרינא,
keivan dechtiv kra achrina, another verse says אשר תאכל האש את העולה,
asher tochal ha'esh et ha'olah, that the fire consumes the עולה olah
על המזבח, al hamizbe'ach, on the altar, אי בעי הכי עביד ואי
בעי הכי עביד, ei ba'ei hachi avid vei ba'ei hachi avid, you
could do it either way. You could put the fire on top
of it or it on top of the fire. The גמרא Gemara
says תיקו, teiku, we don't have an answer. Now again, it's essentially
the exact same question it asked by the קומץ, kometz, except here
it's got a פסוק, pasuk, and again I think that's
significant. All of a sudden the קומץ kometz is not being compared
to blood, the קומץ kometz is being compared to things that are
burnt on the מזבח mizbe'ach because that's what you do with your
קומץ. kometz. But normally the things that you burn on the מזבח
mizbe'ach are not מתירים, matirim, are not the things that make the
קרבן korban valid. They're like after the קרבן korban is valid you
put this stuff on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the fat, the meat, and
so on. So here, and there we never spoke about like a
formal act, a process of putting it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. The
point is you get it up there and it burns. So how
much is the קומץ kometz the same idea of just making sure
it's up there and burning or how much is there a formal
of placing. And again, the fact that the גמרא Gemara raises the
exact same question of it on top of the wood, the wood
on top of it by something like the fat and the meat,
seems to be that we're not really talking about a formal act,
but we're talking about like is this a legitimate way of it
burning, that it's underneath the wood. Okay, let's read the last question.
בעי רבי יצחק נפחא, Bai Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha, רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi
Yitzchak Nafcha asked: אברים שסדרן בצדי המערכה מהו? Evarim shesidran b'tzidei hama'aracha,
mahu?
Let's say you put the limbs of an עולה, olah, not on
top of the firewood, but right next to the firewood. What is
the הלכה? halacha? מהו? mahu? What, it's still going to burn. Right.
Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha? אליבא דמאן דאמר על ממש, Aliba
d'man d'amar al mamash, if you say על al literally means on,
like you know, so it has to be on the, on the
עצים, etzim, על העצים, al ha'etzim, so לא תיבעי לך, lo tivayei
lach, there's no question. It's not on. דעל העצים כתיב, D'al ha'etzim
ktiv, it says on the firewood. כי תיבעי לך, Ki tivayei lach,
what's my question? אליבא דמאן דאמר על בסמוך. Aliba d'man d'amar al
besamuch. If על al can normally mean nearby, sometimes we say that
the word על al means nearby, like על ירך המזבח צפונה. al
yerech hamizbe'ach tzafona. It doesn't mean on the side of the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, it means near the side of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So מאי?
mai? הכא נמי על בסמוך? Hacha nami al besamuch? Would we say
here too the word on the firewood means near the firewood? או
דלמא על העצים דומיא דעל המזבח? O dilma al ha'etzim dumya d'al
hamizbe'ach? No, we'll explain the word על al in context. So it
says you put the limbs on the wood on the altar. So
the same way on the altar literally means on the altar, we
don't mean it's enough to put the limbs of the עולה olah
near the altar, so מה התם על ממש, mah hatam al mamash,
the same way on the altar literally means on it, אף הכא
נמי על ממש af hacha nami al mamash here too it literally
means on. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know
the answer, we left that as a standing question. Okay, so here's
the question about how the stuff have to be burning on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. But again, the question is is this how it has
to be sort of situated, or is this speaking about an act
of placing? It sounds much more like it's an issue of how
it's situated, and therefore again, the whole comparison suggests that the קומץ
kometz is in certain ways much less like
blood. It's not an act of putting it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
but it's just the fact of its burning. Okay, and with that
we actually for now are going to, I mean, one little tiny
little wrap-up משנה, mishna, we are now going to be in a
major shift, and because the next משנה mishna will talk about, we
officially start today's דף כז, daf kaf zayin, and because this משנה
mishna is going to talk about which parts of something prevent the
other part from being valid, we're going to take a whole little
ride throughout all of הלכה halacha and all of שס Shas to
talk about when things consist of multiple components, whether the component, each,
whether the whole, whether each component is actually necessary or not. So
let's take a look.
Is that going to be okay? We're okay. Do you want to
move that to the table though?
So that maybe the wire is to... okay. Okay.
All right. We can move that to the table if that, all
right. If you're okay. Riff, do you want to squeeze a little?
So okay on the, yeah, looks okay.
All right. So keep on going. I don't know if anybody watches
the video anyway. All right. So let's take a look now at
the
משנה. mishna. הקומץ מיעוטו הקומץ, Hakometz mi'uto hakometz, when you have the
קומץ, kometz, מיעוטו מעכב את רובו. mi'uto me'akev et rubo. Even a
tiniest amount, right? You need the entire קומץ. kometz. And if you're
missing even one little piece of it, the whole קומץ kometz is
invalid. So the way that's being framed, you could just say you
need all of it, but the, or a different way of framing
you need all of it is even the smallest part of it
prevents the 99% of it from being valid if you're missing 1%.
The minority holds back the
majority. Interesting questions about democracy
also. Okay. עשרון מיעוטו מעכב את רובו. Isaron mi'uto me'akev et rubo.
The עשרון isaron of flour that makes up the מנחה, mincha, you
need a full עשרון, isaron, and if you're lacking even a tiny
amount, that holds back the majority. היין, Hayayin, how about the wine
that comes with sacrifices, from the, you know, מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim,
מיעוטו מעכב את רובו? mi'uto me'akev et rubo? If you don't have
the full amount of wine that the תורה Torah prescribes, then even
the smallest amount holds back the entire wine from being valid. השמן,
Hashemen, the oil that comes with the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, or
that comes with any מנחה, mincha, whenever the תורה Torah has a
מנחה mincha that has oil and it prescribes a specific amount, מיעוטו
מעכב את רובו. mi'uto me'akev et rubo. Even if you're missing a
tiny amount, it prevents the majority from being valid. הסולת והשמן מעכבין
זה את זה. Hasolet v'hashemen me'akvin zeh et zeh.
Now, this becomes a little bit more interesting. This is not just
saying you need a full amount as the תורה Torah says, you
know, it has to be a לוג, log, it really means a
full לוג, log, but here we're talking about when you have different
components, to what degree is every component necessary, or some components can
survive without the others? For example, I mean to give you an
easy example where this is not the case, with a קרבן korban
comes the מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim. If you don't have the קרבן,
korban, you're not bringing the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, right? Obviously, but
the flip is not true. If, even if you didn't have the
מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, the קרבן korban is still valid. So obviously
there are situations of dependence where one can survive without the other.
We're going to look at a series where there are components where
every single one needs every other piece. Okay, so let's take a
look. הסולת והשמן מעכבין זה את זה Hasolet v'hashemen me'akvin zeh et
zeh by a מנחה, mincha, the flour... The flour and the oil
hold back one another. Right? It's not a good מנחה Mincha without
the right amount of flour and without the right amount of oil
and without them being mixed properly. הקומץ והלבונה מעכבין זה את זה.
Hakometz vehalevona me'akvin zeh es zeh. The הקומץ Kometz and the לבונה,
Levona, the hand-breath of the מנחה Mincha and the frankincense that was
placed on the מנחה, Mincha, they are interdependent because if you don't
have both, the מנחה Mincha is not valid. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara is going to be very straightforward, just quoting how we
know this from פסוקים, pesukim, again with the assumption that it's not
enough that the תורה Torah says you must do it, but there
has to be some type of emphasis or repetition to say that
without it it's not valid.
So let's see the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Where do
we know this from? So we're just going to go down the
list of the משנה. Mishnah. We start with הקומץ. Hakometz. אמר קרא
מלא קמצו תרי זימני. Amar kra melo kumzo trei zimnei. The פסוקים
pesukim say the fill of your קומץ kometz twice, so that means
that you really need the fill and anything less than the fill
is not valid.
עשרון מיעוטו מעכב את רובו מאי טעמא? Issaron mi'uto me'akev es rubo
mai ta'ama? How do we know that the עשרון issaron of flour,
if you don't have the full amount, it's not good? אמר קרא,
Amar kra, the verse says מסלתה, misolta,
its סולת, solet, with the emphasis of it, so somehow that it
means the full amount. אם חסרה כל שהוא פסולה, Im chasra kol
shehu psula, if the smallest amount is lacking, it's invalid. היין מיעוטו
מעכב את רובו? Hayayin mi'uto me'akev es rubo? How do we know
wine, the wine that comes with a free-will sacrifice with עולות olos
or
שלמים? shelamos? How do we know if you're lacking even a small
amount? Because the תורה Torah says ככה, kacha, so. The פסוק pasuk
says ככה יעשה לשור האחד או לאיל האחד, Kacha ye'aseh lashor ha'echad
o la'ayil ha'echad, so shall you do for each ox or for
each ram. So the emphasis of you must do it thusly, maybe
a better translation is thusly, you know, that means that if it's
done in any other way without the exact amount, it's invalid. Yes?
Question.
For some of the קרבנות korbanos that are obligatory, I understand that
there might be precise standards, but for other קרבנות korbanos where
you're not obligated to bring them and you're doing it just as
an expression of...
Right. Let me ask you a question, Rachel, in your business, do
you ever sometimes have volunteers?
Yes. Okay, if you have a volunteer can they do it any
way they want because they're volunteering their time? No. Okay, so that's
the same idea. It's very nice that you have a free will
and you desire to do it, but once you're bringing a קרבן,
korban, there's a way to bring a קרבן. korban.
Okay. All right, fine. I accept. Okay. Now what actually
is interesting is that the גמרא Gemara does learn out much more
variety and latitude than is in the תורה. Torah. The גמרא Gemara
says the concept of מנחה, mincha, they broaden the concept of מנחה
mincha to mean that I can give straight קטורת, ketores, I can
give straight oil, I can give wood, you know, so the range
of objects that are allowed the גמרא Gemara actually, you know, expands
what's in the תורה. Torah. Even there it might define that if,
you know, there's a certain minimum amount that you have to give
and so on. But you know, once even if you're coming here
by your own initiative, once you're here you gotta do it our
way. That's basically the logic. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. השמן, Hashemen, I think we were up to that. השמן מיעוטו
מעכב את רובו. Hashemen mi'uto me'akev es rubo. So oil, even the
smallest amount makes it, you know, prevents it from being good by
any מנחה, mincha, whether it's the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim that comes
with an animal קרבן korban or straight מנחות. minchos. So we have
different פסוקים. pesukim. דמנחת נסכים, De-minchas nesachim, by the מנחת נסכים, minchas
nesachim, ככה, kacha, the word so shall you do, like we quoted
before, exactly this way. ומנחת נדבה, U-minchas nedavah, when it comes to
the free-will מנחה, mincha, אמר קרא ומשמנה, amar kra u-mishamnah, you shall
take from its oil, so the possessive its tells you that it
has to be exactly this way. אם חיסר כל שהוא פסולה, Im
chiser kol shehu psula, if any is lacking, it's invalid. Now we
get to the component parts being holding back one another, interdependent. השמן
והסולת מעכבין זה את זה. Hashemen vehasoles me'akvin zeh es zeh. How
do we know the oil and the flour hold each other back?
מסלתה ומשמנה. Misolta u-mishamnah.
It says its oil and its flour, which means that they are
interlinked. Now that does not tell you that it only says it
once. We need something to underscore it to say that without it
it's no good. So it says it again. מגרשתה ומשמנה. Migeras'ah u-mishamnah.
מגרשתה? Migeras'ah? No, מגרשתה. Migersah. גרסה. Gersah. מגרשתה. Migersah. מגרשתה Gersah means
also flour. Or meal, we might say. Cornmeal.
Cornmeal, yeah, like some. So it basically means flour. So it says
again from its flour and its oil, so that repetition means the
flour and the oil are interdependent. הקומץ והלבונה מעכבין זה את זה.
Hakometz vehalevona me'akvin zeh es zeh. If you need both the הקומץ
kometz and the לבונה, levona, without having both of them the קרבן
korban is not good. על כל לבונתה, Al kol levonatah, it says
twice that you bring the הקומץ kometz with the לבונה. levona. One
פסוק pasuk says you bring it with all of the לבונה, levona,
and the other says ואת כל הלבונה, ve'es kol halevona, and all
of the לבונה levona you offer up. So the repetition אשר על
המנחה, asher al hamincha, so the repetition tells you that without having
both it's not good. Okay, so there's just all this, again, a
lot of these
גמרות Gemaras are going to be straight just. where we get it
from the פסוק. pasuk. By the time we get to י"ז עמוד
ב', yud zayin amud bet, we'll get into a little bit more
of a discussion. But now you are going we have to actually
going to see that we are now going to start the rest
of the פרק perek going far afield from anything having to do
with מנחה mincha and which will eventually get us to extended discussions
about things like תפילין tefillin and מזוזה mezuzah and so on and
we'll see why. Yes.
We learn it just from the fact that it's written twice? Yes.
And if it was written once you would have latitude?
The general principle by קרבנות, korbanot, ironically this is very different than
all other cases. Like we don't say the תורה Torah says you
shall take, you shall eat מצה—well matzah that does say it more
than once—but whatever. You shall blow the שופר shofar on ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. Oh well it only said it once, so no big
deal. We don't say that, right? We normally assume that every specific
detail is required. By קרבנות korbanot the general principle is that you
need שנה עליו הכתוב לעכב shana alav hakatuv l'akev that you need
the תורה Torah to repeat it to say that it holds it
back. And probably the reason is because there is so much of
a wealth of details. I mean it is a little ironic. We're
in the middle of reading ויקרא. Vayikra. Details, details, details. You would
think if anything you have to do according to the exact ritual
it's קרבנות. korbanot. But חז"ל Chazal understand differently. They understand there are
so many details it can't be that you need everything to be
done this way for it to be good. So therefore to know
that it's not just how it should be done ideally but that
it needs to be done this way or else it will be
invalid, you need the תורה Torah to either repeat it or to
underscore it. So that's the general principle by קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so
now let's take a look at the משנה. mishna. Starts again still
with קרבנות korbanot but soon shifts gears. שני
שעירי יום הכיפורים מעכבין זה את זה. shnei se'irei Yom Hakippurim m'akvin
zeh et zeh. The two goats of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the
one you send לעזאזל l'Azazel and the one that you slaughter and
sprinkle the blood in the inside the היכל. Heichal. They prevent one
another. If you only have one and not the other you cannot
proceed. And a lot of the גמרא Gemara in יומא Yoma and
the משניות mishnayot talk about what happens if something happens to one
before the other is done. Blood spilled of one of the goat.
What do you do about the goat you're supposed to send
לעזאזל? l'Azazel? The goat לעזאזל l'Azazel dies, what do you do about
the blood? So both of these need to be around for them
to be valid, although the way in which they're offered is quite
distinct from one another. And here we are getting a little more
interesting. It's not like the קומץ kometz and לבונה levona which are
sort of offered together. You know, here they start together but then
the process is very different. And nevertheless you need both around and
both to be valid in order to continue to do one or
the other one. Okay, so that's the two goats of יום הכיפורים.
Yom Hakippurim. שני כבשי עצרת. shnei kivsei Atzeret. Now we get back
to a little more obvious cases. The two lambs of the special
קרבן korban you bring on שבועות Shavuot with the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem are מעכבין זה את זה, m'akvin zeh et zeh, hold back
one another. If you don't have both lambs the קרבן korban is
not good. שתי חלות מעכבות זו את זו. shtei chalot m'akvot zu
et zu. The two loaves of שבועות Shavuot hold back one another,
and if you don't have both loaves then you have not fulfilled
your obligation of שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. שני סדרים מעכבין זה את
זה. shnei sedarim m'akvin zeh et zeh. The two columns of bread
of the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim hold back one another. And if
you don't have both columns it's not valid and you can't eat
the remnant. You can't say well I didn't have both columns but
I had one and now we brought up the לבונה levona now
I'll eat what's left. At least that half is good. No, it's
one unified קרבן korban of two components and if you don't have
both halves it's not good.
Not good means you have to throw it away?
Exactly. I mean you have to burn it, whatever. And you're right.
Exactly. Okay. Similarly, שני סדרים מעכבין זה
את זה. shnei sedarim m'akvin zeh et zeh. שני בזיכין מעכבין זה
את זה. shnei bezichin m'akvin zeh et zeh. The two cups of
the frankincense that are on the שלחן, shulchan, on the table that
has the stacks of bread, the columns of bread, those hold back
one another. So if you only have one of those then you
can't burn it and say you fulfilled your obligation. You need both
in order to fulfill your obligation. זה את זה. zeh et zeh.
הסדרים והבזיכין מעכבין זה את זה. hasedarim vehabezichin m'akvin zeh et zeh.
Similarly
the columns of the bread and the בזיכין bezichin that are filled
with לבונה levona with the frankincense hold back one another. You can't
burn the frankincense without the bread and you can't eat the bread
without burning the frankincense. So those things all go together. A lot
of this is obvious since it's like one big קרבן. korban. The
least obvious was the first case of the two goats. Now we
turn to other, we shift a little bit. Let's take a look.
שני מינים שבנזיר. shnei minim shebanazir. The two types of things which
a נזיר. nazir. What is two types of things? The שלמים shlamim
of the נזיר. nazir. No, we'll get to that in a minute,
but still we're still in the direct קרבן korban area. The שלמים
shlamim of a נזיר nazir comes with two types of bread. So
you need both of those types of bread in order for it
to be valid. ג' שבפרה. gimmel shebaparah. Now we're getting closer to
what רבקה Rivka was thinking about. The three things that you do
for the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. What are the three things?
אגודת אזוב, agudat ezov, right? You have hyssop. ועץ ארז, ve'eitz arez,
right? Which is cedar wood. ושני תולעת. ushnei tolaat. And you have
a scarlet string. So you need all those three. וד' שבתודה. ve'dalet
shebatodah. We're just bouncing from one to the other. Let's just take
two, three, and four. But the four of the תודה todah we're
now about to. But the four of the תודה, Todah, we're now
back to bread. A תודה Todah has four different loaves of bread.
So if you have only, not four loaves, forty loaves actually, but
four different types of bread. If you don't have all forty, all
four types, then the loaves are not valid. You need all of
the loaves. Because that's reasonable, you could say, 'okay, I only had
thirty loaves, I only had three types, at least those loaves will
be okay, but I didn't fulfill my obligation of the other loaves.'
No, if you don't have all the loaves then none of the
loaves are valid. Okay, but again, it's very different going to like
which parts of the קרבן korban are valid as opposed to a
טהרה taharah process that you're doing for like פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah,
you know? And now the גמרא, Gemara, and now if you really
want to shift, ארבע שבולב, Arba ShebeLulav,
your four species of the לולב, Lulav, right? So here we go.
So, oh wow, that was interesting. I wasn't expecting something that relevant,
practical, right? So the לולב, Lulav, the אתרוג, Etrog, the הדס, Hadas,
and the ערבה, Arava, if you don't have all of them, you're
not יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of לולב. Lulav. You don't get
three-quarters credit. You get zero
credit. Okay, וארבע שבמצורע, V'Arba ShebeMetzora, the four things of a מצורע.
metzora. What are the four of the מצורע? metzora? Again, it's the
אזוב, ezov, the שני תולעת, shni tolaat, the עץ ארז. eitz erez.
So those three things, but also what you also have is the
birds. You dip, you know, you slaughter the birds and you get
their blood and then you dip this into, into the blood of
the bird. So those are the four sort of ingredients in order
to purify the מצורע, metzora, this week's פרשה. parsha. All of these
מעכבין זה את זה, maakvin zeh et zeh, hold back one another.
Do you see the organizational principle here in the משנה? Mishnah? Once
we sort of got to the... right, right, it's completely numerical, which
is why we have a bizarre shifting from bread to the hyssop
to back to bread to back to hyssop because we're just doing
a numerical ordering. Okay, which now we turn from two, three, four,
the next number is seven. The next number of significance. שבע הזיות
שבפרה Sheva Hazayot ShebeParah מעכבות זו את זו. maakvot zo et zo.
By the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, you slaughter it outside the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and you sprinkle from its blood seven times towards
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So if you don't have all seven
sprinkles, it's not good. Similarly, שבע הזיות של בין הבדים, Sheva Hazayot
Shel Bein HaBadim,
when you bring the קרבן korban inside, you know, on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings it, the seven sprinklings
he does between the staves of the ארון Aron and the seven
sprinklings he does שעל הפרוכת She'al HaParochet towards the curtain, right, when
he leaves the קודש הקודשים Kodesh HaKodashim and he faces the curtain,
שעל מזבח הזהב, She'al Mizbeach HaZahav, or that he does on the
golden altar. Now the sprinklings on the curtain and on the golden
altar are not only for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, they're also for
פר העלם דבר Par He'elam Davar and the פר כהן גדול Par
Kohen Gadol what we learned about in הוריות Horayot of the few
other types of inner חטאות chattaot that are done on the inside.
In all of those, מעכבות זו את זו. maakvot zo et zo.
You don't do one, it's like you did none. Okay, and you
need to do the entire set. All right, that was a lot
of different things. Let's take a look. Yes, please.
How do they reconcile something like בל תשחית Bal Tashchit with all
the food that ends up getting thrown away?
You mean if you don't have everything done correctly. You know, I
mean בל תשחית Bal Tashchit worries me less than the other issue,
which comes up in the מקדש, Mikdash, which is צער בעלי חיים,
Tzaar Baalei Chayim, when you have things like, you know, you can't
let this animal, you can't be מקריב makriv it, you can't be
פודה podeh it, so like you let it die. You know, the
basic answer is that these sort of ritual demands trump those
concerns. בל תשחית Bal Tashchit is an easy עבירה aveirah to not
transgress. I mean although our good Jewish mothers taught us, you know,
there're kids starving in Africa and it's בל תשחית Bal Tashchit anytime
we don't, you know, use something to its fullest, basically according to
the גמרא, Gemara, anytime there's some legitimate purpose about why you're doing
what you're doing, it's not wanton destruction. To be בל תשחית Bal
Tashchit it really has to be wanton destruction. So if the purpose
is, let's say you know, let's say the גמרא Gemara says, let's
say you know a close relative dies and somebody does קריעה kriah
on an Armani suit, that's not בל תשחית Bal Tashchit because that's
a way of giving expression to their grief. So if that's true,
certainly you know doing something because of religious problems or הלכה halachah
problems about you know, this is sanctified, it can't be used and
this is just what gets done, it's not technically בל תשחית Bal
Tashchit in terms of the הלכות halachot of בל תשחית.
Bal Tashchit. Maybe it's not... I'm just thinking about the wasting.
You're not asking the הלכה halachah question, you're asking the wasting question.
You know, right, I understand, I understand.
I don't have a good answer other than to say that if
some of the things had not reached the level of קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, then some of the things you would be able to
be פודה. podeh. But there are things that they reach a certain
level and there's no going back and, you know, that's just these
concerns trump,
for better or worse. שני שעירי יום הכיפורים, Shnei Seirei Yom HaKippurim,
let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. The two goats of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur מעכבין זה את זה. maakvin zeh et zeh.
How do you know that? חוקה, Chukkah, it says by יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, it says that this is going to be a חוק.
chok. Where does it say that? It says, let's see, רש"י Rashi
quotes it, והייתה זאת לכם לחוקת עולם, V'hayta zot lachem lechukat olam,
like this shall be a חוקת עולם, chukat olam, it says at
the end of אחרי מות, Achrei Mot, at the end of the
עבודה avodah of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So every part of the
יום כיפור Yom Kippur sacrifice has to be be done exactly this
way. Now of course it's not really a full answer because why
don't we say, well, if you don't have let's say
the ox of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you can't have the goats
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur because it says חוקה. chuka. There's still
a, you know what I mean, it's not like every single component
holds back every other component. There's still some type of conceptual grouping
that goes on here that says, this is a unit and these
are units and so on. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is not getting
into that. We have the idea of חוקה chuka that everything has
to be done right and we're going to group them. And we're
going to say the two goats have to be—are interdependent. שני שעירי
עצרת מעכבין זה את זה. Shnei seirei atzeret me'akvin zeh et zeh.
The two lambs of שבועות Shavuot are interdependent. הויה. Havayah. It says
it shall be because it says by—it says by it—let me just
check רש"י Rashi again. He quotes it. What does it say? סלת
תהיינה. Solet tihyena.
It says fine flour it shall be, but again that's a פסוק
pasuk that's talking about the שתי הלחם shtei halechem that comes with
the lambs. So we apply the words of it shall be even
to the lambs themselves. It has to be exactly that way. שתי
חלות. Shtei challot. So the two loaves of שתי הלחם shtei halechem
of שבועות Shavuot certainly הויה. havayah. It says it shall be. It
has to be exactly that way. שני סדרים. Shnei sedarim. The two
columns of bread by the שולחן. Shulchan. חוקה. chuka. It says חוק.
chok. What does it say חוק? chok? So רש"י Rashi says מאשי
ה' חק עולם. Me'ishei Hashem chok olam. Okay, so it shall be
a חוק עולם. chok olam. It says by the loaves of bread
חוקה. chuka. שני בזיכין. Shnei bezichin. And similarly by the בזיכין bezichin
חוקה. chuka. It says the same פסוק pasuk of חוק. chok. It
has to be exactly that way. הסדרים והבזיכין. Hasedarim vehabezichin. How do
you know the columns and the בזיכין bezichin hold each other back?
Again חוקה chuka because it says חוק. chok. So, you know, you
gotta appreciate a type of a discourse where you don't have to
quote a פסוק. pasuk. You can just quote one word and everybody
knows what you're talking about. חוקה, chuka, yeah, it says חוק chok
here, says חוק chok there. Okay, so it's all covered. It's all
מעכב זה את זה. me'akev zeh et zeh. Okay. Now. You can
maintain the same rule and just quote
חוק. chok.
No, but here it actually is a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, I might
say that—well, that's what I said before by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
It says חוק chok but it doesn't tell you exactly the scope
of the חוק. chok. Right. Now by the case by the שולחן
Shulchan and the bread, we are pretty much saying you need everything.
If you don't have the bread, you don't have this, you don't
have one piece, you don't have the other, everything is required. But
by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, we group things in certain ways. Right?
We don't say by יום כיפור Yom Kippur that if you can't
do the פר par of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you can't
do the שעיר. se'ir. Okay. Or maybe we do, but we're not
saying it here. You know. So anyway, okay, so let's take a
look. שני מינים שבנזיר. Shnei minim shebanazir. The two types of loaves
by a נזיר, Nazir, if you need one in order to have
the other. How do we know that? דכתיב כן יעשה. Dechtiv ken
ya'aseh. It says so shall be done. It says that by the
נזיר. Nazir. כן יעשה על תורת נזרו. Ken ya'aseh al torat nizro.
ג' שבפרה. Gimel shebeparah.
How do you know by the פרה אדומה parah adumah you needed
it to all the three things to be that way? You know,
the עץ ארז, eitz erez, the שני תולעת shni tola'at and the
אזוב. eizov. So it says חוקה זאת חוקת התורה. Chuka, zot chukat
hatorah. This is the law of the תורה. Torah. Okay.
ד' שבתודה. Arba shebetodah. The four types of breads by the תודה.
Todah. If you don't have one type, you don't have the others.
דאתקש לנזיר De'itkash lenazir because תודה Todah is linked to another. How
do you know it? דכתיב Dechtiv it says by the תודה Todah
על זבח תודת שלמיו, Al zevach todah shlamav, you shall bring these
breads with the slaughtering of the תודה Todah of his שלמיו shlamav
sacrifice. ואמר מר Ve'amar mar שלמיו, shlamav, why does it have to
say the word his שלמים? shlamim? That's a superfluous word. לרבות שלמי
נזיר. Lerabbot shalmei Nazir. So we link the שלמי נזיר shalmei Nazir
to that of a תודה Todah for other purposes, which are not
our concern. But once they're linked, so the same way by נזיר
Nazir the loaves of bread are interdependent, by תודה Todah as well
the loaves of bread are interdependent. If you don't have some loaves,
you don't have the other. We will eventually get out of פסוקים
pesukim and have some discussion.
I think—maybe you answered this a bit. We're talking about—let's say you
need all four of the תודה—four Todah types of whatever. Right. And
you don't have one entirely or you don't have enough of one.
Let's say you have like 90% of one.
Right. That's not being discussed here. Presumably—I mean, we did discuss before
in the first משנה Mishnah about מיעוטו מעכב את רובו. mi'uto me'akev
et rubo. When there's a full complement and it's in a—discussed the
תודה. Todah. But presumably I have to check, but presumably by the
תודה Todah you need the full number as well, but that is
not being discussed here. Here it's discussing, we are now in the
mode of not discussing the full שיעור, shiur, the full quantitative amount
of something. We are discussing different components. When something consists of different
components, when the—when each component is necessary and is interdependent. Okay, so
now we go
on. Okay. וד' שבמצורע. Ve'arba shebemetzora. The four things of a מצורע
metzora which are again the אגודת אזוב, agudat eizov, the שני תולעת
shni tola'at and the עץ ארז etz erez as well as the
birds. How do you know that all those are necessary? דכתיב Dechtiv
זאת תהיה—ah, Zot tihyeh this week's פרשה. parsha. זאת תהיה תורת המצורע.
Zot tihyeh torat hametzora. This is the תורה Torah of the מצורע.
metzora. So תורה Torah means or maybe it's from the word זאת,
zot, it has to be this way. It has to be exactly
that way. ורש"י Ve'Rashi says it's from the word תהיה. tihyeh. Okay,
so it has to be exactly that way. All right.
Now, does one bird—Again,
we're not talking about that. We're just talking about—not talking about quantity,
we're talking about different components. Now we get to something that there's
actually a little discussion about and actually is directly relevant to us.
ארבעה שבלולב, Arba shebalulav, the four species of the לולב, Lulav, how
do you know that you can't take one of them and at
least get some partial credit? Because it says ולקחתם, u'lekachtem, you shall
take, so we make the דרשה, drasha, what does ולקחתם u'lekachtem mean?
We sort of divide the word: לקיחה תמה. lekicha tama. So תם,
tam, not just אתם, atem, you shall take it, but תמה, tama,
it has to be a full taking, it needs all the components.
אמר רב חנא בר רבא: Amar Rav Chana bar Rava: לא שנו
אלא שאין לו. Lo shanu ela she'ein lo. When is it a
problem if you don't have all of the ארבעה מינים? arba'ah minim?
If you don't have them, you don't actually own all of the
ארבעה מינים. arba'ah minim. אבל יש לו, Aval yesh lo, if you
have all of the ארבעה מינים, arba'ah minim, אין מעכבין, ein me'akvin,
then they do not—they do not hold each other back. Meaning, what
does that mean? If I own a לולב lulav and an אתרוג
esrog and a הדס, hadas, but I only take one, I'm יוצא?
yotze? So no, as we're going to see in a minute in
the גמרא, Gemara, what it means is they don't have to be
taken as a unit. You don't have to put them in an
אגד, eged, you don't even—you don't have to take them as a
unit. Just to the point that
תוספות Tosafot quotes הלכות גדולות Halachos Gedolos and the רמב"ם Rambam rules
this way, that not only do you not have to put them
in an אגד, eged, you don't even have to all take them
in your hands at the same time. That you can pick up
the לולב lulav and then pick up the אתרוג esrog and then
put it down and then pick up the הדס hadas and put
it down, pick up the ערבה arava and put it down, and
as long as you've taken all four, you are יוצא yotze and
they don't have to be taken as a unit. What?
It doesn't have to be simultaneous?
No, that's at least the way הלכות גדולות Halachos Gedolos reads this.
The גמרא Gemara is going to say what it minimally means is
it doesn't have to be in an אגד, eged, okay? You don't
need that wrapping around, the אגד. eged. But there are ראשונים Rishonim
and גאונים Geonim who understand that although it says לקיחה תמה, lekicha
tama, a whole taking, which might suggest exactly that, the act has
to be a single act that consists of everything, you can actually
have four acts. And therefore, because you could have—it's interesting—you could have
taken them all together, then even when you take them separately, we
view it as if they were taken together. Basically as if they
were taken together. The רמב"ם Rambam goes so far to say that
if you wind up taking them separately, well, you don't make the
ברכה bracha of אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על נטילת לולב, asher kiddishanu
b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al netilas lulav, but when you take
the—if I remember correctly, this is how the רמב"ם Rambam rules—when you
take the אתרוג esrog you say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על לקיחת
פרי עץ הדר, asher kiddishanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al lekichas pri eitz hadar,
and when you get to the הדס hadas you say אשר קדשנו
במצותיו וצונו על פרי עץ הדר כפות תמרים ענף עץ עבות, pri
eitz hadar kapos temarim anaf eitz avos,
and when you get to the ערבה arava you say אשר קדשנו
במצותיו וצונו על ערבי נחל, asher kiddishanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al arvei nachal,
and you actually make separate ברכות. brachos. Which finally gets us to
a question that we are going to be dealing with for many,
many דפים, dafim, which is when we say things hold each other
back, are we saying they're one act, one מצוה, mitzvah, and these
are its components? Or are we saying, no, no, no, they are
distinct מצות, mitzvos, but sometimes even though they're distinct, you in order
for one to count, the other has to be done as well?
So the fact that the רמב"ם Rambam says, and again, I'll double
check, but I'm pretty positive that the רמב"ם Rambam says you can
make separate ברכות brachos suggests that you could think of them as
separate מצוה. mitzvah. But you're not יוצא yotze any one unless you've
done all four. Now that is very bizarre. It's—we could understand that
by like תפילין של יד tefillin shel yad and תפילין של ראש,
tefillin shel rosh, which we're going to discuss. Okay, there you could
understand that you see them as distinct מצות mitzvos that almost always
come together but nevertheless they are actually distinct. By the לולב, lulav,
by the לולב lulav you have one—right, and they're going to say
they're not מעכב me'akev anyway. By the לולב lulav you have one
verb. The one verb is ולקחתם, ulekachtem, right? By the תפילין tefillin
you have two verbs. It says
וקשרתם לאות על ידך והיו לטטפת בין עיניך. ukshartem l'os al yadecha
v'hayu l'totafos bein einecha. By לולב lulav you have one verb, ולקחתם
לכם. ulekachtem lachem. So therefore, logically we would say by the לולב
lulav it is not four acts, it is not—it's certainly not four
מצות. mitzvos. It's one מצוה, mitzvah, one act. Maybe we can allow
you to do it as distinct acts and say since you could
have done it all together, since it was יש לו, yesh lo,
you had them available and you could have done it all together,
we view it as if you did it all together. Basically as
if you did it all together. But the idea that you would
go so far as to make separate ברכות brachos is really quite
striking. That's not in this גמרא, Gemara, but that is a רמב"ם.
Rambam. So let's take a look at this—at what the גמרא Gemara
says to elaborate on this. Yes.
It's a tough concept, though. I mean, it would be on a
case-by-case basis, right?
Exactly. And that is what most of the rest of this פרק
perek is going to be doing. Looking at a range of different
מצות mitzvos and asking: how do the pieces relate to one another?
Okay, so let's take a look.
So someone mentioned, wasn't it רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who פוסק pasken
לולב צריך
אגד?
lulav
tzarich eged?
We're getting—yes, that's exactly what we're going to get introduced. Well, no
we don't, but let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר רב חנא בר רבא לא שנו אלא שאין לו
אבל יש לו. Amar Rav Chana bar Rava: Lo shanu ela she'ein
lo, aval yesh lo. If you have all four מינים minim available
to you, אין מעכבין, ein me'akvin, they don't hold one another back.
מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on this: we have a ברייתא. braisa.
ארבעה מינים שבלולב, Arba'ah minim shebalulav, the four different species in the
לולב, lulav, שנים מהן עושים פירות, shenayim mehen osim peiros, two of
them make fruit—right, the אתרוג esrog and the לולב, lulav, which makes
dates—ושנים
מהן אין עושים פירות,
ushnayim mehen
ein osim peiros, and two don't make
fruit. העושה פירות יהו זקוקים לשאינו עושה פירות ושאינו עושה פירות יהו
זקוקים לעושה פירות. Ha'oseh peiros yehu zekukim leshe'eino oseh peiros v'she'eino oseh
peiros yehu zekukim l'oseh peiros. But the הלכה halacha teaches that it's
not just that the ones that don't make fruit are dependent on
the fruit-makers. Oh no, the fruit-makers... But the fruit makers are dependent
on the ones that don't, and the ones that don't are dependent
on the ones that do. There's a moral message that's going to
come out from here, okay? ואין אדם יוצא ידי חובתו בהן עד
שכולם באגודה אחת. v'ein adam yotzei yedei chovato bahen ad she'kulam b'agudah
achas. You don't fulfill your obligation until they're all in one bundle.
And here's the moral message: וכן ישראל בהרצאה v'chen Yisrael b'hartza'ah and
same the Jewish people when they come to find favor for God.
You know רש"י Rashi says the specific context, although it's not clear
at least from the part quoted, is when they're like having a
תענית ta'anis a fast day and they want God, you know, to
turn to them and to accept their prayers. Now the association to
the fast day might be the general linking of לולב lulav and
the waving of לולב lulav and the whole thing about הושענא רבה
Hoshana Rabbah as the time when everybody is praying for rain and
you want God to answer prayers. So עד שכולם באגודה אחת. ad
she'kulam b'agudah achas. They all have to be in one bundle. שנאמר
הבונה בשמים מעלותיו ואגודתו על ארץ יסדה, she'ne'emar haboneh bashamayim ma'alotav va'agudato
al eretz yesadah, the one who builds in the heavens his like,
you
know, his structures, his edifices, and his bundle, thank you, is established
on the ground. So when his bundle is together, when the Jewish
people are unified, then it sort of
God, you know, dwells properly in the heavens and then God will
be responsive to us. Now I do want to say, you know,
the general sort of message here is, and תוספות Tosafot elaborate and
רש"י Rashi elaborates on that, you know, even though so the ones
who do the תורה, Torah, those are the ones who do מצוות,
mitzvos, the ones who don't do the פירות peiros are the רשעים
resha'im who don't do מצוות, mitzvos, and nevertheless we still need unity,
we can't exclude the רשעים. resha'im. Which is a very nice message,
but I actually think that the message is going further because it
even pointed out that it's not just that the ones who don't
do פירות peiros need the ones who do פירות, peiros, but you
know, the ones need the ones who don't. Now you could say
you need them for this value of unity, that why do we
need them? Because we shouldn't be excluding Jews because of the value
of unity. But you know, the language suggests more than that. The
language suggests that even those who don't do פירות peiros in a
certain way, you know, they actually provide things that those who do
פירות peiros aren't doing and that, you know, they might not always
be as obvious and as the type of fruit, but they provide,
you know, very important parts, you know, as qualities to the Jewish
people that are not always provided by those that are let's say
doing the more traditional forms of Jewish practice.
Rav Kook seems to build on this in terms of
the building of the ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael.
What? Yes, the building of מדינת ישראל. Medinat Yisrael.
That was only available through those who weren't doing.
Right, you don't have too many תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that were
going there and cutting down the trees and planting the, you know,
the swamps and planting the eucalyptus trees and so on. Exactly. שקויעח.
Shkoiyach. So okay, very nice little מוסר mussar and now we see
that they all are required. But we said that they're not required.
So the גמרא Gemara says
תנאי היא. tanna'ei hi. What? I said they're required, אמר עד שכולם
באגודה אחת, amar ad she'kulam b'agudah achas, one bundle tied together.
Right, all four.
Which we do not, I was waiting for somebody to ask that.
Nobody says you tie the אתרוג esrog together. Okay? So? What? We
put it in. Well, there actually is an opinion of the תנאים
Tanna'im that the אתרוג esrog has to be small enough so you
could hold it in the same hand with the לולב. lulav. But
let's read the פסוק pasuk and then I will respond to your
question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא, tanna'ei hi, you're
right, it's a debate of תנאים Tanna'im whether they have to be
in an אגודה. agudah. דתניא לולב בין אגוד בין שאינו אגוד כשר,
de'tanya lulav bein agud bein she'eino agud kasher, the לולב lulav whether
it is bound or not bound is כשר. kasher. רבי יהודה אומר
אגוד כשר שאינו אגוד פסול, Rabbi Yehuda omer agud kasher she'eino agud
pasul, if it is bound it is
כשר, kasher, if it is not bound it is invalid. מאי טעמא
דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Yehuda? Where does Rabbi Yehuda get this
idea that it needs to be bound up? גמר קיחה קיחה. Gamar
kicha kicha. He learns a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah of קיחה קיחה
kicha kicha מאגודת אזוב. me'agudat ezov. It says ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון,
u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon, take for yourself this לולב, lulav, and it
also says you shall take an אגודת אזוב, agudat ezov, this bundle
with the אזוב ezov and the
cedar wood, you know, for some, you know, exactly some of the
things we were talking about before, פרה אדומה parah adumah etc. So
מה להלן באגודה, ma lahan b'agudah, there it says אגודת אזוב, agudat
ezov, a bundle, אף כאן באגודה, af kan b'agudah, here too a
bundle. ורבנן לא גמרי קיחה קיחה V'rabbanan lo gamri kicha kicha and
they don't buy into this גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Now? Because, you
don't have to buy into every גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah.
In one case you're provided with the string.
Good point. כמאן אזלא הא דתניא, K'man azla ha de'tanya, who is
it going like that which we teach in a ברייתא: braisa: לולב
מצוה לאוגדו ואם לא אגדו כשר, Lulav mitzvah le'ogdo v'im lo ogdo
kasher, it's a מצוה mitzvah to make a, put it in a
bundle, but if not it's still valid? כמאן? K'man? Who is that
like? אי כרבי יהודה לא אגדו אמאי כשר? Ei k'Rabbi Yehuda lo
ogdo amai kasher? If it's like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
why is it כשר kasher if it's not bundled? He says it's
required. אי רבנן, Ei Rabbanan, if it's the Rabbis, מאי מצוה? mai
mitzvah? What's the מצוה mitzvah to put it in a bundle? What
do you mean? You just hold it all together. Who needs a
bundle?
You say it's a מצוה.
mitzvah. So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם רבנן ומהי מצוה משום זה
אלי ואנוהו, Le'olam Rabbanan u'mai mitzvah mishum zeh keili v'anveihu, it is
the Rabbis, and what's the מצוה? mitzvah? Because that looks more beautiful.
Now I want to make a couple of הלכה halakha points here.
First, Rachel's question: even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does not require it
all to be in one bundle. The גמרא Gemara learns out from
the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון פרי
עץ הדר u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon peri eitz hadar and then there,
פרי עץ הדר, peri eitz hadar, there's no ו. vav. כפות תמרים...
kapot temarim... וענף עץ עבות וערבי נחל. V'anaf Etz Avot V'arvei Nachal.
So there's no ו vav that links the פרי עץ הדר Pri
Etz Hadar to the כפות תמרים Kapot Temarim to say that even
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda they're not literally in the same
bundle. Of course, the language here of עד שיקולם באגודה אחת ad
sheyekulam b'aguda achat is a little strange, which is why I would
turn to the point that Rachel says is that how much according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda this idea that in theory they at
least conceptually have to be bundled even if not physically. And the
idea that you hold them together, you know, we're very מקפיד makpid
even if we have in different hands, we put them next to
each other, and there is an opinion the same hand, maybe how
much is that part of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's idea even if
in physically the אתרוג etrog is not bundled up. That's one point.
Is it actually a מצוה mitzvah though to try to bundle them?
No, no, nobody ever says. Now, the other point about why we
say it's a מצוה mitzvah according to us, we don't rule like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So the language of זה קלי ואנוהו Zeh
Keili V'anvehu makes it sound like it's just cause, you know, it
looks pretty. And then the emphasis of doing the bundle would be
the way that looks most attractive. However, it could be understood in
a very different way. This גמרא Gemara is saying, you know, seems
to say that at the conceptual level, the rabbis agree that it's
one taking, right? You might not need to physically bundle them, but
at least at a conceptual level, it's one taking. So understood that
way, the idea of מצוה לאגדו mitzvah l'ogdo is not just it
looks prettier. The idea of מצוה לאגדו mitzvah l'ogdo might be that
that makes it the fuller sense of taking it together as a
unit. The difference would be that then you would less emphasize the
aesthetics and more emphasize the degree to which you really have made
them a unit. So for example, the גמרא Gemara says that according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda when it's a מצוה mitzvah to make
it a bundle, you need to do a double knot and you
need to use the actual species of the לולב lulav itself. So
when I take my לולב, lulav, what I do is I don't
use those accordions because they're not a double knot, you know what
I mean by those accordions, right? Although some say it counts like
a double knot because it holds it tightly enough. Anyway, what I
do is I forget that whole thing. I take a strip, I
rip off a strip of a leaf of the לולב, lulav, you
know, then I kind of half it down vertically and I make
strips from it and it works great like string. And then I
take my thing and I make double, with this string-like לולב lulav
thing, and I make double knots to hold the המינים haminim to
the לולב. lulav. I gotta tell you, it looks nicer too. You
know, it really looks more natural. Like it looks like a flower
when you've, you know, you've just got it all coming together, not
this funny accordion thing. But that is understanding that the מצוה mitzvah
of the אגד eged is not the aesthetics of the אגד, eged,
it's defining it as one unit. The more you can define it
as one unit, that might not be מעכב. me'akev. That's the whole
point, it's not מעכב. me'akev. It doesn't mean you're not יוצא, yotzei,
right? But ideally, that is the goal. So that seems to be
it. What? But if you look at the אתרוג, etrog, what you're
leaving... Well but even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda admits. That's the Torah
just sets it aside, it doesn't have the ו. vav.
But this is but the context here is freelancers.
I know. The דרשה drasha of the עושים פירות osim peirot and
the אינם עושים פירות einam osim peirot I understand. So we have
to say that as a virtual level, not at a physical level.
I mean, yeah.
Why do you say it doesn't have a ו? vav? It says
פרי עץ הדר ו... pri etz hadar v'... So the...
No, it says ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון פרי עץ הדר כפות תמרים...
Ulekachtem lachem bayom harishon pri etz hadar kapot temarim... no, it doesn't
have a... Let's get a פסוק. pasuk. It doesn't have a ו.
vav. Here, hand me this סידור. Siddur.
Here. Whoops, that's right.
Okay, it's right. So it's from the...
for the לולב. lulav.
Oh, is it? Okay, I'm looking at the קריאת התורה, Kriat HaTorah,
alright. Either way.
But the context of this whole thing is to do it exactly
this way.
Right, but the exactly this way is the פסוק pasuk not the
beautiful דרשה drasha of עושים פירות osim peirot and אינם עושים פירות.
einam osim peirot. It's true it was a beautiful דרשה drasha and
it explicitly mentioned the אתרוג, etrog, okay, but it's not literally true.
So
what about the אתרוג etrog that's coming in?
We don't really need all four?
Exactly! The ארבעה מינים? arba'ah minim? Exactly!
They can manage by themselves, the ones that do the מצוות. mitzvot.
Exactly!
ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון
פרי
עץ הדר כפות תמרים וענף עץ עבות וערבי נחל.
Ulekachtem lachem bayom
harishon pri etz hadar kapot temarim v'anaf etz avot v'arvei
nachal.
So that's what you see from the Jewish World UJA Federation.
It's
the Orthodox Union. Right, exactly. Oh my god, this is a great
דרשה, drasha, I enjoy. Okay, anyway, so that's what we said. So
even according to the רבנן Rabbanan it's taking them together. The narrow
reading of this is
you could take it without an אגד eged but the אגד eged
again is ideal maybe for aesthetics or maybe even making it more
united. As I said, the הלכות גדולות Halachot Gedolot and the רמב"ם
Rambam go one step further and say בדיעבד bedieved if you own
all four, you can even do four separate acts of taking. But
still, again, the ideal is taking them together.
Would you make a ברכה bracha on the last point? Do you
think that... or would you make a ברכה? bracha?
No, that's I think the... again if I'm remembering correctly, the רמב"ם
Rambam has you making a ברכה bracha on each one individually.
The separate ברכה? bracha?
Yes. Okay, according to the הלכות גדולות Halachot Gedolot no, presumably you
would make it at the beginning and then you would take them
sequentially. But even with this... What?
You just keep making the same ברכה? bracha?
No, you would say על לקיחת פרי עץ הדר, על לקיחת כפות
תמרים, על לקיחת ענף עץ עבות, al lekichat pri etz hadar, al
lekichat kapot temarim, al lekichat anaf etz avot, okay?
Assuming to take it דרך גידולן.
derech gidulan. Yeah, yeah. Okay, so now we say, back to... that
was quite an interesting little digression. So now back to קרבנות *Korbanos*.
Oh, שבע ההזאות שבפר מעכבות זו את זו *sheva ha-haza'ot she-ba-par me'akovot
zu et zu*. The seven sprinklings of the פר *par* hold each
other back. חוקה *chuka*, again it says חוק *chok* by the פרה
אדומה *parah adumah*. שבע הזאות שעל בין הבדים ועל מזבח הזהב ועל
הפרוכת מעכבות זו את זו *sheva ha-haza'ot she-al bein ha-badim v'al mizbe'ach
ha-zahav v'al ha-parochet me'akovot zu et zu*. The sprinklings of the inner
חטאות *chata'ot* on the between the staves of the ארון *aron* and
on the פרוכת *parochet*, all of those things are required and hold
each other back. שביום הכפורים *she-be-Yom Kippurim*, by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*,
דכתיב *d'chtiv* חוקה *chuka*, it says חוק *chok* by יום הכפורים *Yom
Kippurim*. רש"י *Rashi* quoted it, we said it earlier, it says והיתה
זאת לכם לחקת עולם *v'hayta zot lachem l'chukat olam*. דפר כהן המשיח
ופר העלם דבר של ציבור *d'par kohen hamashiach u'par he'elam davar shel
tzibbur*, the inner חטאות *chata'ot* of the פר *par* of the כהן
גדול *kohen gadol* and of the העלם דבר *he'elam davar*, what we
learned about in הוריות *Horayos*, ודשעירי עבודת כוכבים *u'dis'irei avodas kochavim* and
the goats of עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*, which also when it's done
in the communal level become an inner חטאת *chatas*, כדתניא *k'd'tanya*, we
taught in the ברייתא *baraita*: ועשה לפר כאשר עשה לפר הראשון *v'asa
la'par ka'asher asa la'par harishon*. So it says by פר העלם דבר
*par he'elam davar*, you do like it like you did by the
פר *par* of the כהן גדול *kohen gadol*. These are by the
inner חטאות *chata'ot*. מה תלמוד לומר *ma talmud lomar*, why does it
say do like you did it? The Torah makes it very explicit
you do the exact same thing, so why does it then have
to say you're doing the same thing? לכפול בהזאות *l'chpol ba-haza'ot*,
to repeat, to double up the הזאות *haza'ot*, meaning to tell you
it's like it repeated it to tell you that everything is necessary.
שאם חיסר אחת מכל המתנות לא עשה כלום *she'im chisar achat m'kol
hamatanot lo asa klum*, that if you were lacking any one of
them, you didn't do everything, every single of the sprinklings is required.
Okay, we're going to have to end in about five minutes because
I just have to rush off to something. תנו רבנן *tanu rabanan*,
our rabbis taught: שבע הזאות שבפר *sheva ha-haza'ot she-ba-par*. So now we're
on כ"ז ע"א *kaf zayin amud aleph*. The seven sprinklings of the
פרה אדומה *parah adumah* towards the מקדש *mikdash* שעשאן בין שלא לשמן
בין שלא מכוונות פסולות *she-asan bein shelo lishman bein shelo m'chuvanot psulot*.
Whether you did it שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*, okay, cause the Torah
calls the פרה אדומה *parah adumah* חטאת *chatas*, it you know, so
it says חטאת *chatas*, so therefore because it's called a חטאת *chatas*,
what's the הלכה *halacha* if you do a חטאת *chatas* שלא לשמו
*shelo lishmo*? Going all the way back to the first משנה *mishna*
of זבחים *Zevachim*, פסול *pasul*. Okay, so if you did the sprinklings
of the פרה אדומה *parah adumah* שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*, פסול *pasul*.
But now there's also another question which is שלא מכוונות *shelo m'chuvanot*.
You sprinkled but not directly towards the בית המקדש *beit hamikdash*. It
says you shall sprinkle אל נוכח פני אהל מועד *el nochach pnei
ohel mo'ed*. What if you were a little bit off, or a
lot off? So that also invalidates, פסולות *psulot*. ושבפנים ושבמצורע *v'shebifnim v'shebimtzora*,
the sprinklings that you do of an inner חטאת *chatas* or of
a מצורע *mtzora*, the אשם *asham* of a מצורע *mtzora*, שלא לשמן
פסולות *shelo lishman psulot*. If you do it שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*,
it's פסול *pasul*. Why? Cause it's a חטאת *chatas* done שלא לשמו
*shelo lishmo*, it's invalid. The question is by מצורע *mtzora*, it's not
a חטאת *chatas*, it's an אשם *asham*. So we're going to talk
about what it means by a מצורע *mtzora* when it says it's
פסול *pasul*. שלא מכוונות
*shelo m'chuvanot*, let's say it's not exactly on target. You do, right,
so the Torah says that by these inner חטאות *chata'ot*, you sprinkle
on the פרוכת *parochet* towards you know, the center of the קודש
קדשים *kodesh kodashim*. Let's say you're a little bit off, you don't
do it towards the center, you do it on the left, you
do it on the right, or when you sprinkle the blood of
the מצורע *mtzora*, you do it towards the היכל *heichal*. Let's say
you're a little bit off, is it כשר *kosher* or not? So
there it says כשרות *k'sherot*. There בדיעבד *b'diavad* it's okay. So שלא
לשמו *shelo lishmo* is still a פסול *psul*, it's always a פסול
*psul*, but there's a difference if you're a little bit off whether
you're talking about the פרה אדומה *parah adumah* or you're talking about
the inner
חטאות *chata'ot*. והתניא *v'ha tanya*, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, wait one
minute, so we're going to talk about it through showing a problem.
But didn't we teach differently in a ברייתא *baraita*? What did we
teach in a ברייתא *baraita*? גבי פרה שלא לשמן פסולות שלא מכוונות
כשרות *gabei parah shelo lishman psulot shelo m'chuvanot k'sherot*. So first we're
talking about the other direction. We thought that by a פרה אדומה
*parah adumah*, שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* is no good, again it's a
חטאת *chatas*, but if it's not exactly in the right direction, it's
כשר *kosher*. So that everything is כשר *kosher* if it's not exactly
in the right direction. So here we have certainly by things that
aren't פרה אדומה *parah adumah* that's true, and now we have a
debate even by פרה אדומה *parah adumah*. So let's just see a
little bit of the answer and then we'll end for today. אמר
רב חסדא לא קשיא הא רבי יהודה הא רבנן *amar Rav Chisda
lo kashya ha Rabi Yehuda ha rabanan*. It's a debate of רבי
יהודה *Rabi Yehuda* and the רבנן *rabanan*, and I'm just going to
tell you what they're going to say, but we're not going to
have a chance for nuances today, which is there's going to be
a huge debate of רבי יהודה *Rabi Yehuda* and the rabbis, which
is when the Torah says, right, actually coming up on אחרי מות
*Acharei Mot*, that it says nobody else can come into the קודש
*kodesh*, to the קודש קדשים *kodesh kodashim*, ולא ימות *v'lo yamut*. Right,
it says ואל יבא בכל עת אל הקדש מבית לפרכת אל פני
הכפרת אשר על הארן ולא ימות *v'al yavo b'chol et el hakodesh
mibeit laparochet el pnei hakaporet asher al ha'aron v'lo yamut*. Nobody else,
only the כהן גדול *kohen gadol* on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, else
you're חייב מיתה chayav mita *chayav misa*, not by a בית דין
*beit din* but בידי שמים *b'yedei shamayim*. So the question is when
the Torah says do not come, it says you shall not enter
אל פני ה... *el pnei ha...* ואל יבא בכל עת אל הקדש
מבית לפרכת אל פני הכפרת *v'al yavo b'chol et el hakodesh mibeit
laparochet el pnei hakaporet*. So מבית לפרכת *mibeit laparochet* is anywhere in
the קודש קדשים *kodesh kodashim*. אל פני הכפרת *el pnei hakaporet* means
directly facing the ארון *aron*. So there's going to be a debate
that there's going to be those that say that you're only חייב
מיתה *chayav misa* when you're directly facing the ארון *aron*. And when
it says
basically אל פני הכפרת *el pnei hakaporet*... about saying whether we literally
mean facing the ארון or not. So based on that sort of
unrelated debate of when you're חייב מיתה if you enter into the
קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, we're going to say whether the תורה Torah
is exact, means itself means exact when it says you have to
sprinkle towards the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, whether it means exactly towards
or anywhere in that region. Okay, so we will look at that
tomorrow and we will continue to talk about which components are מעכב
me'akev or not.